<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Improve in Improv]]></title><description><![CDATA[My personal journey throug improv comedy]]></description><link>https://ginogalotti.github.io/improv</link><image><url>/images/gino_cover.jpg</url><title>Improve in Improv</title><link>https://ginogalotti.github.io/improv</link></image><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2019 21:24:42 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ginogalotti.github.io/improv/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[So you are planning a frat-party improv show]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div id="preamble">
<div class="sectionbody">
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Improv theatres like to experiment with new and colourful formats, people can only watch so many Harolds before craving crazier shows. That is why frat-party style shows sound very appealing to audiences and theatre managers! Recently we started doing it <a href="https://www.improvcomedy.eu/">at the theatre I&#8217;m part of</a> and I have spent a lot of time thinking of how would I craft my favourite version of it. In this post, we will explore together the elements that can enhance this kind of shows!</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="sect1">
<h2 id="_what_do_i_mean_with_a_frat_party_show">What do I mean with a frat-party show?</h2>
<div class="sectionbody">
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I am referring to shows that usually involve drinking, games and a notch of enjoying being careless. For instance, this is the excerpt we used for <a href="https://www.improvcomedy.eu/event/wtf-26-01-2/">our What The F*ck show</a>. It is a format which embraces the concept of <a href="https://backline.podbean.com/e/142-loud-proud-and-wrong/">loud, proud and wrong</a>.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>An example of a successful long-running show like this is <a href="https://www.facebook.com/mantowncomedy/">Partytown</a> (previously Mantown) from Toronto, Canada. <a href="https://youtu.be/c9jpVu5xtHA">Here is an old (but gold) video</a> from one of their performances, showcasing how they decided to break many of the "improv rules" (after mastering them) to enhance the concept of the format.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>As described on <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B077VYGK1Z/ref=as_li_qf_asin_il_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=callmegino-20&amp;creative=9325&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;creativeASIN=B077VYGK1Z&amp;linkId=638688ca716c7cb51cc514e54027a8cc">Sam Wasson&#8217;s Improv Nation</a>, improvisation surprised everyone for being an artform where performers could express their ideas freely. There was no recording, writing down or censoring of the shows, which enabled improvisers to use brand names, explore real-life scenarios and share their ideas the same way that two friends would do it! The sincerity and intimacy of the performances were unmatched. We can all admit being inappropriate sometimes, and seeing people embracing that on stage really makes a frat-party show shine!</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="sect1">
<h2 id="_which_are_the_elements_from_this_kind_of_shows">Which are the elements from this kind of shows?</h2>
<div class="sectionbody">
<div class="paragraph">
<p>They can be as varied as any other format. If we didn&#8217;t think that homogeneity is too restrictive to explore creativity, we wouldn&#8217;t be in love with Improvisation! But, of course, the devil is in the details, so let&#8217;s explain which are the elements of my take on this format.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>As a youngster-like party, we have to make it competitive! There are many ways to make improv more competitive (and funnier), like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theatresports">theatresports</a>. It usually involves some short-form games where we can give points and set punishments, and it gets even better when you establish two (or more) teams. We would expand this idea more down below!</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Another distinctive part of this kind of parties is drinking and consuming food (we can learn tons from <a href="https://www.chicagoreader.com/chicago/del-close-an-uncensored-oral-history/Content?oid=898618">Del Close</a>, but try to keep this legal!). Barprov attracts a big crowd (this show is an exalted version of Barprov), so embracing the wrongness of having an inebriate cast might help with the format. And it&#8217;s an easy way to punish performers! Needless to say, disclaim this fact to both audience and performers, and create some guidelines to minimize the risk.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>We want to convey the feeling of a crazy and out-of-control party, so we want everyone to be very engaged with this show! We need to warm them up so they can loudly participate in the games (and votes). We want to make them feel part of the madness. We would work on this topic a little bit more down below!</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>In conclusion, a question that I always ask myself when I work on a format is: What is the feeling we want to create in the audience? My answer: participating in a party which was so wrong, loud and hilarious that feels completely different to any other show they can see. I want to create such an experience that feels wrong when trying to pitch it to their friends. This show is not for everyone, but if you do it right you will create many die-hard fans!</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="sect1">
<h2 id="_how_can_we_embrace_competitivity">How can we embrace competitivity?</h2>
<div class="sectionbody">
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Teams enhance competition! If we share a common colour, we can divide the audience and make them rally together. It also lets us play together (improv really benefits from us wanting others to succeed), while still allowing competition. Having one team captain per team as a host helps with many of the games as well, both engaging the crowd and challenging the performers!</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>A big part of the competition is heightening the stakes, and punishments are a simple tool for that! Pick games with points, so we incentive the performer with the lowest score or we capitalize on some jokes going too far! Think of games like <a href="http://improvencyclopedia.org/games//Sex_with_me_is_like.html">Sex with me</a><a href="http://improvencyclopedia.org/games//Worlds_Worst.html">Worlds worst</a> or <a href="http://improvencyclopedia.org/games/Alphabet_Game.html">ABC</a>.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Use the team captains to make the scenes more absurd, and put the performers on the spot! This won&#8217;t be your artsiest improv, and that is fine! Use the captains to make force some performers to use an accent, to pick another choice, or adding new elements to the scene. Hosts have a huge impact on this format, we will explore some of the ways we can enhance actual games at the end of this post!</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Include some randomness in the equation! This is not an actual sport, and the end goal is delivering an amazing experience to the public (and performers). Don&#8217;t be afraid to include some random (and unfair) elements that will shake up the show! An outside character whose job is to find what is the show lacking can really benefit this format. Are the people not engaging enough? Come on stage and change the rules of the game, or offer new drinks/punishments! Some performers are crushing the rest? Come out and make it harder for them! "Ohh, you a very talky-talky, the next time I hear you using more than 5 words I&#8217;ll shower you!", "ABC seems to be very easy for you in English, let&#8217;s see how you manage in Danish!".</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="sect1">
<h2 id="_how_can_we_make_it_more_engaging_for_the_audience">How can we make it more engaging for the audience?</h2>
<div class="sectionbody">
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Performing this format without audience participation feels as bad as being the only drunk person in a party. But don&#8217;t worry, let&#8217;s explore together the ways we can make this more engaging!</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>As many games involve drinking, you can gauge your crowd to see if we can involve them. Please, do it in a mindful way, and make it so people won&#8217;t feel pushed to drink, always asking for consent and disclaiming what will be required for the participation. We need hosts able to keep the pace and spirit of the show without compromising the public&#8217;s integrity.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>There are many ways to make them participate. If we split the theatre into several teams (so they can focus their cheering!), we can have many punishments or games where a performer has to drink a big amount before a group of audience members from the other team finishes drinking a small amount each.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>As a way to promote buying drinks (the theatre manager will love this format!), we can offer discounts during the intermission for the winning team side of the crowd, as well as free drinks and discounts for the people participating in games. We can also offer themed drinks to support each one of the teams (Red Martini and Grey Vodka), giving extra points at the end to the team who sold most drinks.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>There is nothing more engaging than delivering a funny and crazy show, creating an experience in line with our goal! Make the spectators feel supported regardless of their suggestion, and celebrate when they&#8217;re bold enough to suggest something inappropriate (and in line with the show!). Train your performers to create situations where people are suggested to fill the gap with something naughty!</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="sect1">
<h2 id="_games_that_work_great_and_how_to_modify_them">Games that work great and how to modify them</h2>
<div class="sectionbody">
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Let&#8217;s go through the different kind of short form games you can use, and some modifications to make them more competitive! Having rules that are easy to understand (and to fail) gives us more ways to give punishments! Just keep in mind, this is not about ridiculizing a performer but putting some (the ones who enjoy and can handle it) on the spot! We don&#8217;t win the game beating our opponents, but delivering the funniest experience.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>On witty games (like <a href="http://improvencyclopedia.org/games//One_Eighty_Five.html">185</a> or <a href="http://improvencyclopedia.org/games//Worlds_Worst.html">Worlds worst</a>), I think it works best if we allow performers to jump in as soon as they feel ready. This way, teams that are on their toes would get rewarded! Captains can acknowledge if the same performers are going all the time but adding extra rules to them, like using an accent, limiting the number of words or having to deliver it in rhyme!</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Justification games (like <a href="http://improvencyclopedia.org/games//The_Interrogation.html">Interrogation</a> or <a href="http://improvencyclopedia.org/games/Dubbed_Movie.html">Dubbed movie</a>) can be performed by a team with time limitations or a (completely subjective) point system. The other team (or only the captain) can participate by adding new elements to the scene that the players have to justify; such as props, scene painting on the background or simply trying to distract them.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Guessing games (such as <a href="http://improvencyclopedia.org/games//The_Party.html">The party</a> or <a href="http://improvencyclopedia.org/games/LCD.html">Chain Murder</a>) can be done with the other team helping the audience to inspire suggestions. The time limit can also be defined by some activity: like how long takes the other team to drink or eat something, or how long can one of the members hold a plank.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Scene games (like <a href="http://improvencyclopedia.org/games/Pillars.html">Pillars</a> or <a href="https://learnimprov.com/352/">Should have said</a>) can be performed by players of both teams, having a score based on the performance, or by the same team while are being challenged by the others. If both teams participate, the hosts should focus on getting the performers out of their head!</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="sect1">
<h2 id="_have_you_been_to_a_show_with_this_format">Have you been to a show with this format?</h2>
<div class="sectionbody">
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Ok! No more! As you can observe, I really love theorizing about my hobbies to the point where I have squeezed all the fun out of it.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>So, please, let me know what you think about this kind of improv! Have you participated in any show like this? What did work for you? Have you seen this style before?</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>]]></description><link>https://ginogalotti.github.io/improv/2019/01/28/So-you-are-planning-a-frat-party-improv-show.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ginogalotti.github.io/improv/2019/01/28/So-you-are-planning-a-frat-party-improv-show.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Improv]]></category><category><![CDATA[Improv Comedy Copenhagen]]></category><category><![CDATA[ICC]]></category><category><![CDATA[Backline]]></category><category><![CDATA[Short Form]]></category><category><![CDATA[Mantown]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Gino Galotti]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>